{"tossups": [{"question": "The final portion of an essay by this philosopher claims that not even a valid proof of the existence of god could save mankind from itself. A book by this man claims that new recruits are more often afraid of fear than of death. This philosopher claimed that the responsibility for all of mankind is the source of sadness in an essay that rejects deterministic excuses because of the statement that \"existence precedes essence\". A text by this man analyzes the moment when one gazes at a mannequin and believes it to be real in its section \"The Look\". This author of \"Existentialism is a Humanism\" wrote about searching for his friend Pierre in a cafe in a book that discusses \"bad faith\". For 10 points, name this writer of Being and Nothingness.", "answer": "Jean-Paul Sartre", "category": "Philosophy"}, {"question": "The second track on this album begins with the unaccompanied solo double bass playing three-note \"LONG, short, LONG\" patterns. The last track on this album begins with a saxophone melody over pounding timpani. Near the start of this album, the double bass introduces the four-note motif F A-flat, F B-flat; towards the end of its first track, the band leader uses that motif to chant the name of this album. Elvin Jones plays the drum solo that opens this album's third track, \"Pursuance\", as well as the gong strike at the start of its first track, \"Acknowledgement\". Inspired by its composer's search for the title spiritual concept, this 1965 album was released five years after Giant Steps. For 10 points, name this best-selling jazz album of John Coltrane.", "answer": "A Love Supreme", "subcategory": "Fine Arts Other", "category": "Fine Arts"}, {"question": "A poem by this man opens with a French epigraph comparing countries to pages of a book, all of which he has found to be equally bad. This poet described a man recalling \"his young barbarians all at play\" as \"the arena swims around him\" in an ekphrasis on The Dying Gaul. A poem by this man declares that the title event will occur because \"the sword outwears its sheath\" and \"the heart must pause to breathe\". He dedicated two cantos \"To Ianthe\" of a four-canto poem whose title indicates that its autobiographical hero is not yet a knight. This poet of \"So we'll go no more a-roving\" viciously attacked Bob Southey in the opening of his unfinished satiric epic about an easily-seduced Spaniard. For 10 points, name this English poet of Childe Harold's Pilgrimage and Don Juan (JOO-in).", "answer": "Lord Byron [or George Gordon Byron", "subcategory": "Literature British", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "In Proto-Germanic, this part of speech includes a small, irregular subclass named for two inflections of this part of speech. In Proto-Indo-European, the traditional reconstruction of this part of speech is described by the Cowgill\u00c2\u2013Rix system. In Proto-Germanic, this part of speech is classified based on whether it inflects via ablaut or via a dental suffix. In Germanic languages, this part of speech is satellite-framed, possesses strong and weak forms, and, if it has zero valence, must take a dummy subject. The copula is otherwise known as the \"linking\" form of this part of speech, which can be conjugated to express mood, aspect, or tense. For 10 points, name this part of speech that conveys action.", "answer": "verb", "category": "Social Science"}, {"question": "During a period before this war called ha-hamtana (hah-hom-tah-NAH), a group of women called the \"Merry Wives of Windsor\" protested outside Labor Party headquarters. One side in this war demanded that U Thant (oo-taunt) remove UN peacekeepers in order to blockade the Straits of Tiran from Sharm el Sheikh (shake). Prior to this war, Prime Minister Levi Eshkol called his country's first national unity government, allowing Moshe Dayan (mo-SHEH die-YAWN) to serve as Minister of Defense. This war began with a preemptive strike which crippled the air power of Egypt and Syria, leading to the capture of the Golan Heights, the West Bank and the Sinai. For 10 points, name this 1967 war in which Israel defeated an Arab coalition.", "answer": "Six-Day War [or Third Arab-Israeli War]", "subcategory": "History World", "category": "History"}, {"question": "This process unusually results in Fbw7-mediated translocation of c-Myc to the nucleolus. A pathway analogous to this process is initiated by NEDD8. This process is performed by the p53-binding mouse double minute 2 homolog, and by the SCF complex. Separase activity is disinhibited upon binding of Cdc20 to another RING-finger domain complex performing this process called the APC or cyclosome, which directs securin to a certain 26S structure. In this process, E3 ligase attaches the glycine 76 of a namesake protein to a lysine residue on a condemned protein. For 10 points, name this process in which proteins are targeted for degradation in the proteasome by a namesake omnipresent protein.", "answer": "ubiquitination [or ubiquitylation; or ubiquitin pathway; or word forms; or obvious equivalents, such as adding ubiquitin to a protein]", "subcategory": "Science Biology", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "While on his way to this city, a man has his belt taken by Agabus, who binds himself with it and warns the other man he will suffer that fate. A soldier in this city tells a man he has arrested \"I had to pay a lot of money for my citizenship\" and initially confuses his prisoner for an Egyptian terrorist. In this city, a man says \"it's only nine in the morning\" to defend others from accusations of drunkenness. After being arrested here, Paul is placed on trial in Caesarea (SEE-zah-REE-ah) by Roman governors Felix and Festus. The calling of Matthias occurred in this city's \"Upper Room\", which is also where people began to first speak in tongues. The first Day of Pentecost occurred in this city. For 10 points, the early chapters of the book of Acts are set in what city in the aftermath of Jesus's resurrection?", "answer": "Jerusalem [or Yerushalayim]", "category": "Religion"}, {"question": "A common chemographic projection in petrology involves combining the ACF and AKF diagrams with a ternary diagram for aluminum oxide, iron oxide, and this element's oxide. The komatiite (koh- MAH-tee-ite) igneous suite is characterized by extremely high levels of this element, for which this element is easily the third most abundant by weight after silicon and oxygen. The solid solution series of forsterite, which is this element's silicate, to fayalite, which is iron silicate, is what composes olivine, a major component of mafic and ultramafic rocks. An anhydrous carbonate mineral often formed by the replacement of calcium with this element is dolomite. For 10 points, what alkaline earth metal contributes to the hardness of water because it is a two-plus cation, like calcium?", "answer": "magnesium [or Mg]", "subcategory": "Science Chemistry", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "A character in this novel remarks that \"a man who is born falls into a dream like a man who falls into the sea\", noting that inexperienced people drown because they try to climb out of the water into the air. A character in this novel describes waking up after sleeping for as little as one second on a riverbank while escaping from a jail where he had been asked to repair a clock. This novel's protagonist is betrayed by The Nazarene, leading to the death of Dain Waris. This novel's title character is sent by Mr. Stein to replace Cornelius working in Patusan, where he is called \"tuan\" and marries a girl called Jewel. This novel's title character abandons the apparently sinking Patna while serving as its mate. For 10 points, name this novel narrated by Marlow and written by Joseph Conrad.", "answer": "Lord Jim", "subcategory": "Literature European", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "This man owned Artemisia Gentileschi's Self-Portrait as the Allegory of Painting, and employed Gentileschi's father Orazio late in the artist's life. A Lorenzo Lotto painting of a goldsmith may have inspired a painting that shows three copies of this man, which Bernini used as a basis for a now- destroyed bust of him. A painting of this man's wife also shows Jeffrey Hudson, a dwarf. Endymion Porter tends to this man's horse while he holds a baton in a painting of him at the Hunt. In another equestrian portrait of this man, he appears riding under a triumphal arch while a shield depicting the Stuart coat of arms sits at the bottom-left. For 10 points, name this English king, the subject of many portraits by Anthony van Dyck.", "answer": "Charles I [prompt on Charles]", "subcategory": "Fine Arts Visual", "category": "Fine Arts"}, {"question": "An arrow stuck in this man's face was treated with honey by the royal physician John Bradmore, but still left a permanent scar. Henry Scrope and Richard, Earl of Cambridge, planned the Southampton Plot against this ruler to replace him with Edmund Mortimer. Although Holy Roman Emperor Sigismund acknowledged this ruler's claim to the French crown in the Treaty of Canterbury, it was the Treaty of Troyes (twah) signed with Charles VI of France that ensured his claim through a marriage to Catherine of Valois (val-WAH). At his most famous battle, this king fought Charles d'Albret (doll-BRAY), suffered an attack on his baggage train, and was aided by longbowmen firing up a muddy hill. For 10 points, identify this King of England who won the Battle of Agincourt.", "answer": "Henry V [prompt on Henry]", "subcategory": "History British", "category": "History"}, {"question": "Humans have a short lifespan because instead of marrying the princess of rocks, Ninigi chose instead to marry the princess of these objects, Konohana. The son of Ptah and Bast, Maahes, was often depicted with a blue one of these objects on his head. Clytie (CLY-tee-ee) sat and pined after Helios so much that she was turned into one of them. Mars was conceived parthenogenetically when Juno touched one of these objects. A handsome youth was turned into one of these objects after staring into a pool at his own reflection. After he was killed by a discus hurled the jealous Zephyrus, the blood of another handsome youth became one of these objects. For 10 points, name this part of a plant that Narcissus and Hyacinthus became.", "answer": "flowers [or specific types of flowers, such as cherry blossoms, sakura, lotus, turnsole, heliotrope; or narcissus or hyacinth until they are read] ", "category": "Mythology"}, {"question": "After stealing a necklace from a statue of one of these people, Theodosius I's niece Serena was haunted by bad dreams. These people were responsible for making a type of flour called mola salsa. The Tarpeian Rock is named for one of these people who traitorously allowed the army of Titus Tatius to enter Rome. According to Plutarch, these people were punished by being sealed in a chamber near the Colline Gate with only limited food and water. The pontifex maximus appointed children aged six through ten to become these people for thirty years, during which they guarded the Palladium. By marrying Elagabalus, one of these people controversially violated their vow of chastity. For 10 points, name these priestesses who watched over a sacred fire.", "answer": "Vestal Virgins [or Vestals; prompt on virgins or women] ", "subcategory": "History Classical", "category": "History"}, {"question": "Naval architecture uses a variant of this procedure sometimes known as the 1\u00c2\u20133\u00c2\u20133\u00c2\u20131 rule. G. F. Kuncir (koon-CHEER) proposed the adaptive version of this algorithm, which subdivides the interval of interest repeatedly until an error threshold is not exceeded. The error bound for this algorithm is less than a certain value divided by 2,880, itself multiplied by f-of-x, where x is an input between two points. This method, which corresponds to Newton\u00c2\u2013Cotes quadrature using three points, involves taking two points a and b, summing them, dividing by six, and multiplying that result by f-of-a plus f- of-b and four times f of the quantity a-plus-b over two. Parabolas are used in, for 10 points, what method of numerical integration that is usually more accurate than the trapezoid rule?", "answer": "Simpson's method [or Simpson's rule]", "subcategory": "Science Math", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "This author referred to assassin Charles Guiteau (gee-TOH) as \"a dry tree in which worms have nested\" in his account of Guiteau's trial. Some of his poems became a song, which, as arranged by Pete Seeger, was a hit for the folk band The Sandpipers. That song begins by referencing this poet's lines about being \"a sincere man from where the palm grows\". In an essay dismissing racial hatred, this man proclaimed a \"new America... from the Rio Bravo to the Straits of Magellan\". This man wrote the essay \"Our America\" for a Mexican newspaper and produced the collection Versos Sencillos. He was killed fighting the Spanish at the Battle of Dos Ri\u0301os. For 10 points, name this author of the poem that became \"Guantanamera\", a Cuban patriotic song.", "answer": "Jose\u0301 Marti\u0301 [or Jose\u0301 Julia\u0301n Marti\u0301 Pe\u0301rez] ", "subcategory": "Literature World", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "This author described an actor who disguises himself as an old black man to pay a debt to Major Talbot. He also wrote about the homeless man Soapy, who tries to get arrested so he can spend the winter indoors. This author of \"The Duplicity of Hargraves\" and \"The Cop and the Anthem\" created the artist Behrman, who paints the title object while Johnsy is bedridden with pneumonia. In another of this author's stories, Bill and Sam's plans are thwarted after Ebenezer Dorset demands payment in exchange for taking back his kidnapped son. For 10 points, name this author of \"The Last Leaf\" and \"The Ransom of Red Chief\" whose collection The Four Million also includes \"The Gift of the Magi\".", "answer": "O. Henry [or William Sydney Porter]", "subcategory": "Literature American", "category": "Literature"}, {"question": "A composer from this modern-day country wrote a polyphonic choral piece that sets every other line as a monophonic chant, despite being scored for one four-part chorus and one five-part chorus. Another composer from this country wrote a polyphonic mass that nevertheless sets the Gloria and Credo largely in homophonic texture. That mass is scored for six voices, but ends with a seven-voice reprisal of the Agnus Dei. A composer from this country wrote a setting of the Miserere that was illegal to transcribe until a teenage Mozart did it from memory. It is said that a composer from this country saved polyphony by writing the Pope Marcellus Mass. For 10 points, name this country home to Gregorio Allegri and Giovanni Pierluigi da Palestrina.", "answer": "Italy [or Italia; or Italian Republic; or Repubblica Italiana]", "subcategory": "Fine Arts Auditory", "category": "Fine Arts"}, {"question": "This country is home to the world's only active natro\u00c2\u00b7carbonatite volcano, the \"Mountain of God\" or Ol Doinyo Lengai, which is found to the south of its Lake Natron. Another volcano in this country is the scientific namesake of a baboon-like monkey genus, the kipunji. This country's Mbeya Region hosts Mount Rungwe, and a caldera from a former volcano here comprises the Ngorongoro Conservation Area, which contains Olduvai Gorge. The Kibo, Mawenzi, and Shira volcanic cones adorn another mountain in this country, Africa's highest, which is found near its border with Kenya. For 10 points, name this home of Mount Kilimanjaro.", "answer": "Tanzania [United Republic of Tanzania; or Jamhuri ya Muungano wa Tanzania] ", "category": "Geography"}, {"question": "In free space, examples of these things, which are not beams, take an Hermite\u00c2\u2013Gaussian (air-MEET GOW-see-in) form and are abbreviated TEM. For a Gaussian beam, a measure of how far out the beam goes before the intensity drops by a factor of e-squared is this term's \"field diameter\". Two indices are used to define the \"guided\" examples of these things, abbreviated LP, which are a common object of study in the context of optical fibers. Optical fibers can be divided into those that have one of these things and those that have multiple. For a system of masses, motions in which every mass moves with the same frequency is an example of these things, which occur at integer multiples of the fundamental frequency. For 10 points, name these things that are prefixed by \"normal\" to indicate special motions in a coupled oscillatory system.", "answer": "modes", "subcategory": "Science Physics", "category": "Science"}, {"question": "A writer with this surname wrote about a black woman who foregoes marriage and procreation so that there are less people for whites to abuse in her play Rachel. While giving a speech, a member of this family won a debate against an angry audience member in Amesbury. A member of this family responded to an attack with the \"Letters to Caroline Beecher\", while another member of this family published the tract \"Appeal to the Christian Women of the South\". Those two members of this family worked on a book subtitled \"Testimony of a Thousand Witnesses\". That book, American Slavery as It Is, was co-written by the husband of a member of this family, Theodore Weld. For 10 points, give this surname of Sarah and Angelina, two sisters who took up the cause of abolitionism.", "answer": "Grimke", "subcategory": "History American", "category": "History"}, {"question": "A servant in this location shoos away beggars with the excuse that she needs to eat the scraps herself, and fondly remembers a now-deceased man who used to steal glances up her skirt. In this location, a character is infuriated when a photograph of the man she is interested in is stolen from under her pillow by a hunchback. Troubling news arrives to this location about a local girl out of wedlock who is about to be killed for infanticide. The tyrannical matriarch of this location demands that her daughters observe an eight-year mourning period after the death of her husband, which leads to trouble when two of them have their eyes on Pepe el Romano. For 10 points, name this residence that titles a play by Federico Garci\u0301a Lorca.", "answer": "The House of Bernarda Alba", "subcategory": "Literature European", "category": "Literature"}], "bonuses": []}